黑客们好，欢迎回到pwn学院
hello hackers welcome back to pwn College
这是动态分配器误用模块的续集
this is the next video in the dynamic allocator misuse Module
我们将讨论元数据和chunk
we'll be talking about metadata and chunks
什么是元数据，什么是chunk
so what is metadata and what are chunks
元数据你们已经见过了
well metadata you've already seen
比如在讲Tcache时
and in for example the Tcache lecture
正如你看到的
as you saw in Tcache
当你释放一个chunk的时候
when you free a chunk
chunk这个术语有点提前了
there goes the term chunk I'm getting ahead of myself
当释放一个内存块时
when you free an allocation
该内存块的数据区域
the data region of that allocation where
应用开发人员存储数据的地方
you as an application developer were storing data and so forth
也就是malloc返回的指针
the pointer that was returned by malloc
指向的内存
the part of memory that was pointing to
当内存块被释放时
when the allocation was freed
用户数据区被tcache重用于存储元数据
that area was reused for tcache metadata
构建tcache使用的单链表
to create that tcache singly linked list
这被称为chunk内元数据，或每个chunk的元数据
it turns out this is called in chunk or per chunk metadata
这引出了一个问题。什么是chunk？
and this brings up the question of what is a chunk well
malloc给你的内存地址
turns out that what you see as memory addresses that malloc gives you and so forth
再次声明在本模块中
ptmalloc and again here on this module
我们主要讨论的是
we're talking predominantly about
Linux用户空间malloc实现：Ptmalloc
Linux userspaces malloc implementation of this
这是大多数人在linux中使用的，glibc的malloc实现
the one in glibc which is the standard C library that most people use in Linux
当你调用malloc
when you call malloc
并传入一个size参数
and you give it a size
它会给你一个内存地址
it'll give you a memory address
在这个地址至少有size字节可用的内存
at which there's at least that much the many bytes available
但它真正在内部管理的
but what it really tracks internally
是称为chunk的数据结构
is a data structure called a chunk
malloc返回的地址
and this the address that you are given as a return from malloc
实际上是一个指向chunk内部的指针
is actually a pointer part way into this chunk
第一次听可能有点奇怪
so this is a little bit tricky to wrap your head around
一般使用某个对象时
usually when you are interacting with objects
你会有一个指针指向这个对象开头
you have a pointer to their very beginning
但在这里，malloc没有给你这样的指针
in this case malloc doesn't give you that
在malloc内部，它管理着chunk
inside it tracks its allocations by their chunks
但它只返回给你
but to you it just gives
用户可见的那部分的内存地址
the memory address the user facing part of that structure
chunk的其他部分记录大小信息
the other things in that structure are sizes right
至少在它被使用时的样子（大小信息+用户数据）
at least when the structure is being used
但在释放它的过程
later on of course when you free it
就像我们在tcache中看到的那样
as we saw with tcache
它使用的内存是，额
this part actual used memory is is
原来给应用程序使用的内存
the memory that was used by the application
现在被堆用来存储它的元数据
is now used by the heap implementation  to store it's metadata
在用户内存之前，还存了2个东西
but before that two things are stored
就在返回给你的地址之前
the one thing right before the address that is returned to you
8个字节
the 8 proceeding byte
那里存的就是大小
there's the size
这就是
so this is actually how
释放内存时
when you free an allocation
堆是如何知道内存块有多大的（free的时候不需要传大小）
how malloc knows how much memory was there
它只需要检查一下释放地址的前面
it actually looks right before that address to figure that out
这是一个
so that's one thing
另一个在这个大小前的也是大小
the other thing right before that is actually the size if
这有点复杂
there's a bit complicated
如果前面的chunk没在使用
if the chunk before is not in use
那么这个位置是前一个chunk的大小
then in this location is the size of the previous chunk
就是上一次释放的内存块的大小
the size of the chunk immediately proceeding the chunk that you were just returned
现在malloc保证至少有n字节的空间
now malloc guarantees at least n bytes space
当你调用malloc n
when you call malloc n
chunk的大小是16(十六进制10)的倍数
but the chunk sizes they are multiples of 16 hex 10
所以malloc返回的内存会大于等于你请求的大小
right so it'll actually pad up higher than what you requested
我们马上就会讲到
actually as we'll go through in a second
它甚至比这更棘手
it's even more tricky than this
但基本上
but basically
你会得到一个大于等于请求大小的chunk
you will receive a chunk that is greater than or equal to what you requested
这是malloc唯一能向你保证的
that's the only contract that malloc has with you
好了，让我们来看看它是如何工作的
all right so let's take a look how this works
我创建了一个heap_size程序
I created a heap_size program
来演示这个
to play around with this
这个程序只有一个size命令行参数
all right this program just follows I will take a size on the command line
分配两个size大小的chunk
I allocate two chunks of that size
先释放了先分配的
I free the earlier one
这样我们可以看到prev_size起作用了
so we can see that previous size come into play
不过要真正的让它被free掉，从缓存中去除
unfortunately to really get it free to fight the cacheing
必须像这样做
I have to do this insane thing
分配一个更大的chunk
where I try to allocate a bigger chunk
这样malloc就会遍历它的列表
so that the malloc will go through its list
我一会儿会讲到这个
I'll talk about that in a second
我们现在可以忽略这个
we can ignore this for now
然后我打印出prev_size和chunk大小
and then I will print out the previous size and size of each chunk
这里我执行了setbuf(stdout, null)
alright one thing I'll mention I do this setbuf stdout null
这有什么用?
what does this do
它禁用了libc对标准输出的缓冲
it disables libc's buffering on standard out
我们为什么要这样做
why do we do this
这样做是因为不禁用缓冲
we do this because if buffering is not disabled
那么printf和scanf会在内部使用malloc
then printf and scanf will actually use malloc internally
抱歉，会把这一切搞砸
excuse me and we'll screw all of this up
特别是
especially
不利于观察堆
these stuff won't tell us what we expected to tell us
好了
alright anyways
heap_size
heap size
先试一下不在tcache缓存范围内的大小
let's try it with a heap size that does not fit into tcache first
我们用1050
let's go with 1050
好的我们以1050为大小运行
all right so we run heap size 1050
提供给我们的大小是0x430
hex 430 is what is provided to us
我们来看看这是什么
so let's see what that is
1050是0x41a
so that is so 1050 is 41a
0x41a填充0x15达到最近的16（0x10）的倍数
420 is of course hex 15 padding to the nearest hex 10 to the nearest 16 byte
这才是0x420
and then so that's hex 420
0x430
and then hex 4 3 0
是0x420加上0x10字节的chunk元数据
is that plus 16 bytes for the chunk metadata
这就是chunk的大小
so this is the chunk size
这里有一个1
here we have a 1
这个标志标识前一个chunk
that is the flag that says the previous chunk
a前一个chunk是否在使用中
whatever was before a is in use
实际上在a之前什么都没有
I think actually nothing was before a
可能对于第一个节点，它总认为前面是被使用的
so probably that just always considers the previous thing to be in use
至少不是空闲的
at least it is not free
释放了a后
since we freed a
b就不同了
B is a different story
b的大小是0x430而不是0x431
b has 430 for the size instead of 4 3 1
这意味着，前一chunk是空闲的
that means hey the previous chunk is free
需要的话就可以用
if you need to take it for whatever reason
这就是堆分配器使用的元数据
that is metadata used by the heap allocator
前一个chunk是空闲的
and then since the previous chunk is free
加上分配器有前一个chunk的大小
it also has the previous size there
分配器就知道了
which of course tells the the allocator
这里有多少可用空间
how much is available there
有多少空闲内存可以被使用
how much free memory there is to be able to play around with
例如，如果我
and for example  if I malloc
在这之后malloc一个小内存块
after this some small amount
分配器会从这个空闲块取size大小的内存
it'll likely take it out of this size of that free chunk
然后减小这个size
and reduce that size
这真是太酷了
that's just pretty cool to see
好吧，不管怎样
alright anyways um
实际上
actually
让我们暂时脱离剧本
let's just go off script for one second
看看
and just see it
如果就这么做了呢
what if you just do it all right
我们来看malloc 16
let's do malloc 16
这个大小很合适
that's gonna be nice and small
编译
compile it
运行
run it
可以看到它被分配在a中
you can see that got allocated into a
分配了一个0x20大小的chunk在原来a的位置
so a hex 20 chunk got allocated into where we had a
然后B在别的地方
and then we have B somewhere else
你们是镜像的，所以
you are mirrored so we have
a，然后在它的左边（我们的右边）是B
a and then to the left of that we have B
它非常大。有0x400
and it's very large. it's hex 400
a是十六进制20
a is hex 20
他们中间有一个0x410大小的空闲内存
and in between we have a hex 410 free space
能成功真是太让人兴奋了
super super exciting to have that work
先恢复一下，别一会忘了
anyways let's undo that so I don't forget later alright
酷，这就是size
awesome so that is the size right um
为什么prev_size只在前一个chunk不被使用时有效呢
now why is this prev_size only valid when the the chunk is in use
这是个好问题
this is a good question
回答这个问题之前
actually before we go to that question
先看一下前面忘记讲的
let me show you one thing I forgot to show you
我们看了比tcache缓存范围大的chunk的情况
we so far looked at larger chunks than bin in tcache
如果要看tcache
if you look at tcache
我们用16。16在tcache的范围内
let's do 16. 16 fits in tcache
即使我们释放了a
even though we free a
在程序中，我们释放了它
in our program we will free this guy
但是b的prev_in_use仍然被设置为1
but still b prev_in_use is set to 1
它认为a仍然被使用
it thinks that a is still allocated
这是因为tcache劫持了分配器
that is because tcache just hijacks the allocator
所有小于等于1032字节的内存块
basically completely for small allocations up to 1032 bytes
我在Tcache的课上说错了，说成了1036字节
I accidentally said 1036 bytes in the Tcache lecture
我为此道歉
I apologize about that
tcache劫持了小于1032字节的内存块
but for allocations less than 1032 bytes it just hijacks
它没有真释放它们
it doesn't even really free it
可以说他们一直都被tcache使用
it just grabs it for Tcaches use
因此prev_inuse仍然被设置为1
hence prev_inuse still being set
好吧
all right
酷
cool
那么为什么不使用prev_size呢
so why was previous size not used
正如我们在这里看到的
as we can see here
它是0，尽管前一个chunk的大小是0x20
it's 0 even though the size here is hex 20
这是一件有趣的事情
well that is an interesting thing
这是因为当有两个chunk，假设大小为16
that is because when you have two chunks of size 16 let's say
当然是说malloc 16的chunk
of course those are allocated with a chunk of size 16
它们在内存中彼此相邻
and they just fit next to each other in memory
如果请求一个8结尾的大小
when you have a size that is that ends in an 8
比如24（0x18）
so something like 24
这不会多分配
that doesn't get rounded up
如果你看
if you look
如果我们malloc 16
if we allocate something with size 16
chunk大小为0x20
the chunk size is hex 20. 24
24的话，chunk大小仍然是0x20
the chunk size is still hex 20 and that is
24当然是十六进制18
so 24 is of course hex 18
size占8，prev_size占8
plus 8 for the size,  plus 8 for the pre size
所以chunk大小应该是0x28
that should be hex 28
但这里chunk size只有0x20
but they only gave us hex 20 in our chunk size
是什么让
what gives
是这样的
well it turns out that
当前一个chunk正在使用时
when a previous chunk is in use
堆不会
the heap does not
堆就是这样设计的
just the way it's designed
后一个chunk的prev_size不需要记录前一个chunk的大小
does not have to track it's the previous size of the next chunk
如果chunk a正在使用
right so if Chunk a is in use
chunk b的prev_size无关紧要
Chunk b's previous size doesn't matter
在a是空闲的时后，查看它
it's only valid it's only ever checked
只是因为ptmalloc的实现逻辑
just because of the logic in ptmalloc when a is free
当a被分配时
right so when a is allocated
它可以使用B的prev_size字段
it can use this the prev_size field of B
也就是说，它们正好连上了
which is it's right up against as storage
从表面上看，这是疯狂的
which on the face of it is insane
但
but
是这样的
it is the case
分配时有机会节省8个字节的内存
and it saves every once in a while  8 bytes of mem per allocation
这是一种优化
and so it is an optimization that is used
让我在另一个demo中给你们看一下
actually let me show that to you in another demo
好的，考虑一下
all right so consider
这个heap_metadat_overlap.c
this program heap metadata overlap.c
和之前的很像
it's very similar to our old one
我分配了两个chunk
I allocate two chunks
然后用大写字母A填满chunk a
and then I just fill all of chunk a with Capital As
非常简单，对，这是对的
super straightforward right and and this is correct
我们分配了size大小的内存
we malloced of size
然后全用了
and we're using the full size
这是a
so this is a
如果我们运行这个
um if we run this and we create a
申请16字节
I don't know a 16 byte allocation
size值为0x21
our allocations size hex 21
0x20，而且prev_in_use位 置为1
hex 20 and then the prev_in_use bit is set
chunk的大小是0x20
our chunk's size hex 20
就是16字节的可用空间
so that is our 16 bytes of usable space
加上16字节的元数据
plus our16 bytes of size metadata
但如果请求24
but if I set it to 24
这是16字节的可用空间
this is our 16 byte of usable space
然后还有8个字节(占用prev_size)
and then 8 more
但size仍然是0x20
right the size still hex 20
可以看到B的prev_size被大写的A覆盖了
but you can see the previous size of B was over written with capital As
这不是内存损坏
this is not a memory corruption
这是堆的预期用途
this is intended use of the heap
它与元数据重叠
it overlaps the metadata
对于chunk来说...
for chunks that are
如果当前chunk正在使用，它的数据区会占用后一个chunk的prev_size
the metadata of the next chunk if the current chunk is in use
就是为了节省空间
just to save some space
很疯狂，但就是这样
pretty crazy but that's how it is
好了，那么当chunk空闲时会发生什么呢
all right so what happens when a chunk is free
所以我们看了大小元数据
so we looked around as sizes
我们看了chunk的那部分
we looked around at that part of the chunk
但在现实中
but in reality
当一个chunk是空闲的，就像我们在Tcache中看到的那样
when a chunk is free as we saw with Tcache
chunk还有更多的部分
there is more to the structure
取决于它是什么类型的chunk
depending on what type of chunk it was
这里
um and here
我们必须介绍ptmalloc的不同缓存级别
we have to introduce the different cache levels of ptmalloc
Ptmalloc非常复杂
ptmalloc is very complex
它有数千行代码
it's thousands of lines of code
而且它是不断改变的
it's constantly changing
所以这张幻灯片是一个大概
and so this slide is necessarily an approximation
事实上，这整个模块都是大概
in fact this whole module is of somewhat of an approximation
东西都是不断发展的，以ubuntu2004的libc2.31来说
because though a thing is constantly evolving as of libc 2.31 in ubuntu 2004
基本上ptmalloc有几个不同的缓存层
basically ptmalloc has several different cache layers
当然，嗯
and and definitely uh
基本上这是它们的使用顺序
basically this is their order of use
释放内存块的时候，首先
first when you free something
如果它足够小，就会试着放进Tcache
it goes tries to get put into the Tcache if it's small enough
大小在0到1032之间
it's between size really 0 or size 1 and and and 1032
如果tcache关了、满了或由于某些原因不可用
if tcache is off or full or unavailable for some reason
然后
then
这个chunk会被放到一个类似的东西中，fastbin
the chunk is put into something very very similar,  a fastbin
fastbin 最大能缓存160字节的chunk
for allocations up to 160 bytes
注意，tcache完全覆盖了fastbin
now notice tcache completely covers the fast bins
现在通常只和Tcache互动
usually nowadays you interact with Tcache
如果它也不起作用了
if that doesn't work
这个chunk会被扔到所谓的unsorted bin中
that allocation is thrown into what is called an unsorted bin
这是一个列表
it is a list of
是一个双链表
doubly linked list of
记录着最近被释放的chunk
chunks that had been recently freed
而且这些chunk还没被分到合适的下一层级的bin中
and not yet sorted into better fitting bins lower in the cache hierarchy
所以可以快速获取
this is a fast path to catch
适应频繁free，malloc的场景
you know very quick free reuse type scenarios
把被free的chunk
so you take a chunk that is freed
放到unsorted bin里
you put it unsorted bin
下一次malloc时
the next time a malloc happens
且tcache或fastbin里没有合适的chunk
and Tcache or fastbins can't produce a chunk that's cacheed to satisfy that malloc
我们查看unsorted bin
we look at the unsorted bin
如果找到一个合适的chunk，我们就返回它
if we find a chunk that satisfies it we return it
如果没有，我们就把chunk放到
if not we take that chunk and we sort it into either
64个双链表small bins中，双链表中存储一种大小的chunk
64 small bins of the same size also doubly linked
或者是large bins中，这个双链表可以存储
or a doubly linked list of large bins that can contain
不同大小的chunk
different sized chunks
这非常复杂
this is all incredibly complicated
我想你们不会在作业中用到这个
you're not going to need this I don't think for the the homework
但这就是libc内部的运作方式
but this is how libc works inside
让我们一起来看看
let's take a look at
空闲chunk中的一些元数据
some of the metadata that is placed in the free chunk
您已经看过了tcache元数据 next和 key
you've seen the tcache metadata next and key
如果不熟悉它，可以复习一下上次的课
if this doesn't look familiar go back and review the tcache lecture
对于其他chunk，例如large bin
for other chunks for example for large bins
一旦它们从unsorted bin中取出来
once they are grabbed out of the unsorted bin
如果下一个malloc不能
if the next malloc can't
如果它们不适合下一次malloc
if they can't be used to satisfy the next malloc
它们会被放入一个双链表中
they are put into a doubly linked list
同时也在另一个双链表中，它记录了chunk大小关系
that also has links to bigger and smaller lists of chunks
很复杂
this is a crazy thing
但是基本上是这样的
but but here's basically how it works
相同大小的chunk会存储在一个链表中
the chunks of the same size are stored in a linked list
chunk a有一个前向指针指向chunk B
where chunk a will have a forward pointer that points to chunk B
chunk B有一个前向指针指向chunk C
Chunk B has a forward pointer than points to chunk C
然后chunkC有一个后向指针指向chunkB
then Chunk C has a back pointer that points to chunk B
chunk b 有一个后向指针指向chunk a
Chunk B has a back pointer that points to chunk A
这被称为双链表，其中
this is called the doubly linked list where
每个节点都有链接连接到它的前后节点
each item has a link to the item after and item before it
他们这样做是为了便于
they do this so that you can
从中间取出一个节点，然后返回
take an item out of the middle very easily and return it
单链表很难做到这点
whereas that is hard to do with a single link list
在大小关系链表中也一样
and then they also have the same sort of situation  but between different sizes
如果你有一个很大的chunk
so if you have a large chunk of size
2K字节
2 kilobytes
但是你需要4kb
but you really need 4 kilobytes
你可以查看nextsize指针
you can actually look and follow this next size pointer
然后你看到在large bin里的更大的chunk
and then you see the next larger chunk  that you have available in the large bin
这是malloc内部的复杂实现
again they are just crazy malloc internals
我没有过多的讲 fast bin或者small bins
for completeness notice I'm not talking about fast bins or small bins
因为它们被Tcache完全覆盖了
because they are fully covered in some sense by Tcache
Tcache也覆盖了部分 large bin，large bin从512字节开始
large bins started at 512 bytes which Tcache still covers
但是在1032字节之后
but after 1 000 and 32 bytes
你不就再和Tcache打交道了
you're no longer dealing with Tcache
你要接触的是unsorted bins 和 large bins
you're dealing with unsorted bins and large bins for the cacheing
好吧
all right
另一个
finally another
也许是最后一个概念
maybe the last concept yeah
我们要讲的是wilderness
that we're gonna cover is the wilderness
chunk是从哪里来的呢
where do chunks come from right so
如果我malloc 16
let's say I malloc 16
会发生什么
what happens
首先malloc会查看缓存
well first malloc will look in the caches
它会在缓存中寻找合适的chunk
it'll look in the caches for a free chunk
这些chunk就放在那儿，随时可以取出来
that's sitting around ready to go
查查tcache
it look in the Tcache
如果失败了
if that fails
它会查看fast bin、small bin、unsorted bin，large bins（口误）
it'll look in the fast bin small bins unsorted bin large bins
会依次查看，fast bin、unsorted bin、small bin、large bins
no that the fast bin unsorted bin small bin large bin
如果都失败了
and if that fails
它查看堆末尾的可用空间
it look at the available space at the end of the heap
如果堆的末端有足够的空间
if there's enough space at the end of the heap
在介绍堆的时候
so remember recall in the beginning of the heap introduction
我说的是数据段
I was talking about the data segment
我们追踪并观察了brk 系统调用
we traced through and we watched the brk syscall
libc默认将0x20 000字节映射到堆中
libc maps something like Hex 20 000 byte into the heap by default
所以这里有一些空间
so there's some space there
如果有足够的，它会切下一个chunk
if there is enough it'll slice off a chunk of that
然后返回
and return it
如果不够，而且分配请求的很大
right if there's not enough and the allocation is huge
那么malloc将使用mmap一块内存来返回
then malloc will use mmap to return
创建一个内存区域来满足你的请求
to create a area of memory just for your allocation
然后把它返回给你
and return that to you
如果没有足够的可用空间
if there isn't enough available space
并且分配也不是很大
and the allocation isn't so large
malloc将使用BRK系统调用来增长堆
and malloc will grow the heap using the brk syscall
然后来到2这里，切下一个chunk
and will go to number two to slice off a chunk of it
让我把相机藏起来
let me hide my camera
刚刚没注意这个会盖住侧面
I didn't realize this would cover the side
那么malloc是怎么知道还有多少空间的
alright so how does malloc know how much space is there
它必须存储它
well it has to store it
它把它储存在所谓的wilderness里
and it stores it in what it's called oh the wilderness
wilderness是一个假的chunk
the wilderness is a fake chunk
它位于堆的末尾
it is located at the end of the heap
它基本上只有一个大小
and it basically just has a size
就像其他chunk一样
just like any other chunk
但这个大小说明了wilderness还剩下多少
but that size basicly says how much of the wilderness is remaining
什么时候需要映射更多的内存
and when to actually map more memory so
哎呀，我不知道发生了什么
whoops I don't know what happened there
我创建了这个程序
I created this program
向我们展示wilderness 是如何运作的，
to show us how the wilderness works so we
我们准备好堆
warm up the heap
这条语句的作用是
actually the reason this is here is to
免得printf的缓冲区碍事
get this printf's buffer out of the way
但是你也可以使用setvbuf
but you can also use the setvbuf
这个之前展示过的方法来消除影响
that I showed you earlier to disable the need for that
不管怎样，我们分配内存
anyways we allocate
然后展示wilderness的大小
and then I show you what the wilderness size is
这是最后一次分配
this is the last allocation in the heap
也就是最右边的内存块
the right most allocation
所以它的右边就是wilderness
so exactly to the right of this is the wilderness
wilderness是
and the wilderness is
如果你还记得的话
so if you recall
如果malloc 16，则chunk的大小是0x20
a 16 byte allocation will have a chunk size of hex 20
a在它0x10的位置
and a will be hex 10 into it
所以chunk还剩下16字节
so there's 16 left in the chunk size
A[0]是首个8字节
a[0] would be the first 8
A[1]第二个8字节
a[1] the second 8
A[2]这8字节是下一个chunk的prev_in_use
a[2] are the 8 bit bytes that would be the next chunk's prev_in_use
嗯…
uh...
8字节整型
number 8 byte integer
如果我们的chunk被分配了
and if our chunk is allocated
它不是空闲的
and it's not free
如果chunk还在使用
if the chunk is in use
那么我们就可以安全地使用接下来的8个字节
then we can safely use those next 8 bytes by design
所以a[2]
so a[2]
A[0]是前8个字节。A[1]是第二个8字节
a[0] is the first 8 byte. a[1] is the second 8 byte
A[2]是预留的8字节
a[2] is that reserve 8 bytes
完全可以使用
totally value to use
A[3]是下一个chunk的size元数据
a[3] is the size metadata of the next chunk
我们把它打印出来
and here's where we print that out
然后我们malloc更多
then we allocate more
打印出wilderness大小
print out the wilderness size
现在a是不同的东西，它是下一个chunk
now a is something different it's the next chunk over
我们分配更多
we allocate more
这里我要分配
and here I'm going to allocate
基本上剩下堆的全部
what is basically the rest of the heap
这个0x20，我想实际上是0x21000
you this hex 20 I think actually it was hex 21 000
无论
whatever
我把剩下的都用掉
I eat up the rest of that
然后我会展示剩下的wilderness非常非常小
and then I will show the remaining wilderness is very very small
当我们再次分配的时候
and then when we allocate the next thing
分配器会增加wilderness
it'll grow the wilderness
我们来编译它
so let's compile it
开始吧
here we go
好吧
all right
wilderness开始的大小是 0x20921
we start out here with a wilderness size of 20921 in hex
在分配16个字节之后
after allocating another 16 bytes
这会返回一个0x20大小的chunk
so that of course returns a chunk of hex 20
还剩0x20901，和我们期望的一样少了0x20
we end up with 20901  as we expect 20 less
我们再来一次
we malloc again
又少了20
end up with 20 less
然后我们malloc一个巨大的内存
and then we make a giant allocation
malloc
malloc again
现在wilderness很小
and we end up with a wilderness that is tiny
只剩下0x20字节了
only hex 20 bytes left in our wilderness
如果我们再malloc
if we then malloc again
Libc不会让wilderness空着
libc doesn't like to have an empty wilderness
所以它会用sbrk来重新增大
so it'll use sbrk to grow it again
我应该提一下
I should mention
所有这些打印出的数字都在内存的不同位置
all of these numbers are printed out of a different location in memory
作为我们的
as our
你们是镜像的
you're mirrored
我们的堆向右增长
let me show you as our heap grows to the right
wilderness元数据会被推得越来越远
the wilderness metadata gets pushed out further and further right
当然了，如果它本身还是没问题的
but of course it it still maintains itself properly
我用strace演示一下
alright um let me show you this in strace
这是我们最初设置堆的时候
so here is when we initially set up the the heap
这两个数的差是0x21 000
this is the difference between this two is hex 2 1000
就在7f000到5e000之间
right between 7f 000 and 5E 000
差值是21000
21 000 actually
你们可以看到
and so you can see that
它记录着分配后堆中的可用空间量
that tracks with the amount of space available in the heap after the allocations
这次分配之后
after the allocations
然后当我们分配了这个巨大的chunk后
and then when we make this gigantic allocation
堆里基本没空余空间了
and end up with almost nothing in the heap
下次我们调用malloc的时候
the next time we do a malloc
或者说wilderness里什么都不剩了
or nothing left in the wilderness
下次执行malloc时，libc执行了BRK
the next time we do a malloc libc does a brk
再分配了0x21000字节
and it allocates another 21 000 bytes
从f7 f000来到了fa 0000
so we go from f7 f000 to fa 0000
差值是 0x21 000
that is a difference of 2 1 0 0 0 in hex
然后嗯...
and that is how big our and then we use of course
现在堆里还剩0x21
so we had a remaining hex 21
增加了0x21000
we added hex 21 000
然后我们malloc用完了0x21
then we used up hex 21 for our malloc
然后又有了0x21000，当然还有prev_inuse位
and we ended up with 21 000 with of course the prev_inuse bit set
很酷
pretty cool huh
好了，这就是wilderness
alright so that is the wilderness
这就是libc获得chunk的地方
that's where libc gets its chunks
从wilderness中获取
tames them from the wilderness
最后，我再提一次
and to close out I'll mention once again
这都是关于PTmalloc的
this is all about PTmalloc
glibc中的分配器
the allocator in glibc
是大多数Linux发行版的C库
which is the C library for most Linux distributions
嗯
um
其他分配器是不同的
other allocators are different
不是所有分配器都需要这些花哨的缓存
you don't need all this fancy cacheing necessarily to implement an allocator
很多其他的分配器甚至没有块内元数据
and a lot of other allocators don't even have inline metadata
块内元数据就像我们刚看到的
metadata in the chunks like what we just looked at
Jemalloc就是这样一个分配器
jemalloc is one such allocator
freeBSD的分配器
the allocator of freeBSD
Android，也是Linux
Android which you notice is Linux
但它用的库和用户空间程序与一般发行版非常不同
but it uses very very different libraries and user space programs
包括一个不同的分配器
including a different allocator
Firefox使用Jemalloc
Firefox uses Jemalloc despite
尽管它是一个在Linux上运行的程序
ostensibly being a program that runs in Linux
它仍然可以使用不同的分配器
it can still use a different allocator
Jemalloc没有块内元数据
Jemalloc has no perchunk metadata
这是非常不同的
it's very different
它建立在不同的原则之上
just built on different principles
它也有元数据
it does still have metadata
它只是在内部存储它
it just stores it internally
所以
so
我希望你学到了很多关于chunk的知识
I hope you Learned a lot about chunks
和chunk元数据的知识
and about metadata
在该模块，接下来
and in the rest of the module
我们将学会如何滥用他们
we learn how to abuse them